<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter written by G. L. to M.r And. Kingh. and M.r Tho. Med</title>
            <author>Leyburn, George, 1593-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1938A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33747</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48359)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33747)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1992:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter written by G. L. to M.r And. Kingh. and M.r Tho. Med</title>
                  <author>Leyburn, George, 1593-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Douai? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>G.L. = George Leyburn.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to an unidentified work of Thomas Blacloe (i.e. Thomas White).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>White, Thomas, 1593-1676 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:33747:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <head>A LETTER WRITTEN BY G. L. TO M.<hi rend="sup">R</hi> AND. KINGH. AND M.<hi rend="sup">R</hi> THO. MED.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>VCH HONOVRED SIRS.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I cannot ſufficiently expreſſe how hartily I doe reioyce to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that neither of you haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred by vote, or conſent to the publis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing of M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas Blacloe his printed Pamphlett. For vndoubtedly all good, vertuous, and Religious Catholiques will iudge thoſe that ingaged in ſoe fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le a buſines, to haue contracted a ſtayne or blemish which to wipe awaye lies not now with in their reach. For ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33747:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->from the reproches of Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, Madman, hiſſinge ſerpent, &amp;c. beſeeming Luthers Satyres. the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne conceyned in the ſaid Pamphlett is ſcandalous, and perniciouſe: inſoemuch, that it will neceſſarily reflecte vpon thoſe, who haue countenanced it with their votes, and render their proceeding as vnworthie as the ſaid doctrine is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and worthie to be abhor'd: In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that it teacheth.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<hi rend="sup">0</hi> Againſt the Popes infallibilitie in ſoe ſpightfull a manner, as not any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique writer hath vſed expreſſions of a more Satyricall bitternes againſt it: <hi>viz that it is not defenſible but by force of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and power, ſcandalizeth Catholiques, and auerteth thoſe who otherwiſe were neere conuerſion.</hi> And to theſe expreſſions may be added an other out of the ſaid M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloes reprochfull magazine, which is, <hi>that to maintayne the Popes Infallibility, is as great a ſinne, as is the defloureing of a Sacred Virgin vpon an altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33747:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <p>Now I doe appeale to you, whether this doctrine deliuered by M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blacloe in in the ſaid Pamphlett, auerring <hi>that to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Popes Infallibilitie,</hi> (which is the Aſſertion mainteyned in all tymes by the whole Current of Catholique Doctors) <hi>is ſcandalous, deſtructiue of ſoules, and as great a ſinne as is the deflouring of Sacred Virgins vpon an altar.</hi> whether I ſay this vnworthy doctrine will not neceſſarly render thoſe vnworthy, who haue voted for the publishing of it. how euer I doe firmely beleeue, that the diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath permitted this foule procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding far vnbeeſeeming Apoſtolicall Miſſioners, to the end that our brethren diſperſt in diuerſe Prouinces, may not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reafter be abuſed by the now London Conſult that is ſett at the helme of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 
               <hi>Teacheth, that to auerre the inlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of faithfull ſoules out of Purgatory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of iudgment through the aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Suffrages &amp;c. is contrary to piety,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33747:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->chargeth god with irrationall Iuſtice, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth heauen to auction, that who can giue most shall ſooneſt come thether.</hi> wherefore I doe appeale to you, whether this doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne damning a Catholique veritie defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Pope Eugenius the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Councell of Florence, as allſo by Pope Benedict the 12. eſtablish'd by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant practiſe of the vniuerſall Church, and mainteyn'd by all Catholique wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will not infallibly blemishe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of thoſe, who haue voted in Countenance of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 
               <hi>Teacheth viſions, and apparitions of ſoules relating to Purgatory to be Old wifes tales.</hi> Where againe I doe appeale to you, whether mocking at Apparitions of that nature, related by S. Auguſtine, S. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, S. Bede, and others, will not preiudice the honour of thoſe, who conſented to the ſcandalous calling of them old wifes tales.</p>
            <p>This is all: onely I dare ſay that not any heretique writer hath shewne himſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33747:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->ſoe pernicious in impugning the Popes Infallibility, as M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blacloe: nor any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique writer hath manifeſted himſelf ſoe violent an enemy to the vniuerſall practiſe of Gods Church as M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blacloe: nor ſoe rigid to the ſoules in Purgatory, as M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blacloe: nor ſoe ciuill to diuells and damned in hell, as M.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Blacloe: who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes vnto them, noe other punishment then what their owne pure volitions shall inflicte. And in ſuch a manner, that he neither excludes delight in their pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor a poſsibility of being happy, if they will them ſelues: as it apears by my anſwer to his Letter: where is obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble flexibility in Angells. From which profane Nouelties, ſweete IESVS deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, and giue vs grace to <hi>Sapere ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietatem,</hi> whith shal be the conſtant praier of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Much honoured Sirs</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt aſſured friend and moſt humble ſervant. G. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
